十九世纪中叶
China in the mid-19th century...
清廷腐败 民不聊生
the suffering of its people under the corrupt rule of the Qing dynasty
太平军义举反清
set the stage for the Taiping Rebellion.
中国陷入长达十四年的内战
During the chaos of the 14 years long civil war,
造成死亡人口近七千万
70 million people died in battle or from starvation...
这个数字是第二次世界大战全球死亡人口的总和
The casualties equaled the recorded death toll from WWII.
他说
He said...
那天从死人堆里爬出来
the day he crawled out from the pile of corpses...
他已经死了
he was a dead man.
他还说
He also said...
在这个年代 死 很容易
it was an age when death came easy...
活着的 更难
but living was hard.
我的人都死光了
All my men died.
就剩我一个
I alone survived.
那是你命好
You were lucky.
我装死的
I played dead.
我的兄弟 一千六百多人
My brothers... more than 1600 men...
拼了三天三夜
fought for three days and nights...
都没了
They all died...
魁字营那帮畜生
The Kui army were inhuman.
只站在后面 一动不动
They only stood behind us and watched.
看着我那帮兄弟就这样一个一个的
My brothers were slaughtered one after another.
都没了
No one survived.
他说 那天他遇到了一个女人
He met a woman that day.
在废弃的破屋里过了一夜
They spent the night in a deserted house.
不知是那碗粥 还是那个女人
He didn't know if it was the woman or the soup...
让他感觉 原来他还活着
that brought him back to life.
哪儿有饭吃啊
Where can I find food?
去大街破房子前蹲着
Try the main street.
他说
He said...
第一次碰到我的那天
the first time he met me...
天是灰蒙蒙的 跟他的心情一样
the sky was overcast, like his mood.
可我清楚地记得
But I remember clearly...
那天是个晴天 阳光刺眼
that it was a glaringly sunny day.
吃完就跟我去干玩命的活
Eat your food and let's get going!
吃完 干活
Eat and get to work!
抢啊
Dig in!
你这么能打 跟我
You sure know how to fight.
我带你见大哥
I should introduce you to my big brother!
干什么活
Where are we going?
打劫
To rob!
劫军粮
From the rebel army!
他后来说 你们胆大包天
He later told me he was outraged...
竟敢抢军队的粮食
that bandits like us dared steal from troops.
我说 方圆百里已无粮
What did we care? Famine is everywhere.
饿都饿死了 管他谁的粮
We either robbed or died.
冲出去
Ride out!
杀
Kill them!
快 杀那个领头的
Seize their leader, hurry!
那天 他不但救了我
He saved my life that day...
他还在教我
and taught me a lesson.
打蛇打七寸 擒贼先擒王
Strike the head... and the body will fall.
午阳哥
Brother Jiang...
你看
Look!
是那个人给的
That man gave them to you.
这是将军穿的
They're for generals.
午阳哥做将军了
Brother Jiang has become a general!
你在想什么
What are you thinking about?
想家
My home.
回来了
They've returned!
别急 跟上 跟上 有的吃啦
Come with me! We've got food!
我们今天晚上在这里大吃一顿
I have good news, tonight we feast!
你怎么一个人呢
Why are you alone?
我是从家里头跑出来的
I ran away from home.
听口音 你是扬州人
Is that a Yangzhou accent?
你听出来啦
You noticed?
你怎么还能听出我是扬州口音啊
How could you tell?
你听过扬州瘦马吗
Have you ever heard of Yangzhou Ponies?
就是找些漂亮的小女孩 教她们琴棋书画
You mean pretty young girls who are trained as courtesans...
养大了以后卖给富人做妾 是吧
and sold to rich men?
不过
Yes.
不过我十五岁那年
But when I turned 15...
刚要被卖出去
and was about to be sold...
小时候带我一起玩的朋友
a man came and stole me away.
就把我给抢回来了
He was my childhood playmate.
他还杀了人
He killed a few people.
就带我躲进山里做了匪
We went into hiding and he became a bandit.
他不知道你已经变了
He thought he saved you,
还以为救了你
but you were no longer the same peasant girl.
他是好人
He's a good man.
安心上路
Go in peace!
大哥定的规矩
Big brother laid down the rule...
留下空位斟满酒
to save seats and wine...
敬死去的兄弟
for the brothers who died.
你在军中是个头
Were you a general in the army?
过去的事了
Not anymore.
为何离开
Why did you desert?
来 喝
Drink up!
大家都是朝廷的兵
My troops and the Kui troops.
约好联手消灭敌军
planned to join forces against the enemy.
魁字营出尔反尔
But they betrayed us.
寡不敌众
We were outnumbered...
我的兄弟就这样死光了
and all my brothers were killed!
天大地大 没有兄弟情大
There's nothing more important than the love between brothers.
是吧
That I agree.
这年头没有兄弟
These days, without brothers...
活不下去
you can't survive.
午阳 吃饭了
Wu-Yang, dinner's here.
新招回村的人都会留下吗
Are the new recruits staying?
有饭吃 谁不留下
No one wants to leave when there's food.
对了 来了一个姓庞的 很厉害
Except for Pang, he's not our kind.
他走不走 我就不知道了
I don't know if he's staying or not.
漂亮吧
Pretty, isn't it?
死人身上捡的
I snatched it from a dead man.
你晓得这是什么吗
Do you know what this is?
不知道
No.
保平安的
It protects you.
那晚是真的吗
Did that night really happen?
我一直等在那儿
I waited there for you...
还以为是梦
wondering if it was all a dream.
既然跑了 干嘛还回来
If you ran away, why did you come back?
跑了很多次了
I ran away many times,
想得挺好
had it all thought out.
每次都是回来
But I always ended up back here.
干嘛还回来呢
Why did you come back?
自己的命 该自己做主
You should decide for your own life.
躲在这儿
Stay here!
“魁”
"Kui".
干嘛抢我们粮食
Why are you robbing our food?
你拿个破铁棍子杵我
I dare you to hit me?
你杵啊 你杵啊
Go ahead!
住手
Stop fighting!
你几岁啊 我当你奶奶都成
I'm old enough to be your grandmother!
再动我就开枪了 要死人的
Stand back or I'll shoot!
我不怕你
I dare you!
我真的要开枪 我真的要
I swear I'll shoot...
我不怕死 你打死我吧
Go ahead! Kill me too!
你
You!
都别动
Nobody moves!
你为什么不看着我
Look at me when I speak.
你以为抢了粮车 粮食就归你了吗
You think you can keep the food you robbed?
而今是给你们个机会 报效朝廷
Consider this as a pay back to your country.
走
Let's go!
要是我们有枪 就跟他们拼了
If only we had guns... we could fight them!
那是送死
That's suicide!
这么活着 还不如死
I'd rather die than live like this!
当匪 狗的命 永远被人追
Thieves are always on the run.
为什么不投军
Why not join the army?
投了军有军饷
Once you're in the army...
有了军饷 就可以买粮食养家糊口
you'll receive wages to feed your families.
投了军有枪炮
You'll get guns so...
有了枪炮 就没人敢欺负我们了
that no one will bully you.
这村子才真的太平
This village will finally have peace.
我们是土匪 朝廷能收我们吗
We're bandits, will the army take us?
魁字营嚣张 势大力强
The Kui army is grandiose and powerful.
我们这点儿人 他们根本看不上
They couldn't care less about us.
倒是的军机处的陈公 正缺人手
But Lord Chen's army is desperate for men.
他的绿营兵常被魁字营欺负
He wants to increase his power...
一直想壮大势力
to rival the Kui army.
如果我们投他 那正是雪中送炭
He should welcome us with open arms.
二虎 抓住这个机会
Er-Hu , use this opportunity
让今天的事 永远不要再发生
Then today's event... will never happen again.
好
Alright!
当匪
As bandits...
我们要当最大的
We have to be the biggest!
你以前是清军
You deserted the Qing army,
现下带我们投军 不黑不白的
now you want us to join them? You're a two-faced man.
凭什么信你
Why shall we trust you?
纳投名状
Take the blood oath!
兄弟结义 各杀一个外人
To be blood brothers, we kill an outsider...
断绝后路 以示忠诚
to show our loyalty to the brotherhood.
从此 兄弟的命是命
Only the lives of our brothers count.
其他的皆可杀
The rest are expendable.
那天我问他
I asked him that day.
纳了投名状 永远没有退路
There's no turning back.
你愿意吗
Are you certain?
他没吭声
He said nothing.
我要
Let me...
大爷 怎么回事啊
Masters, what is it?!
狗日的 你干什么啊 没招你们没惹你们的
What are you bastards doing?!
为什么要杀我们啊
What did we do wrong?...
不就是从你们村路过吗
We were only passing through!
大爷 求求你 放 放了我吧
Have mercy on me... please...
记住我这张脸
Remember my face...
下回投胎找我报仇
and take revenge in your next life!
今有庞青云
We, Pang Qing-Yun,
赵二虎
Zhao Er-Hu,
姜午阳
and Jiang Wu-Yang...
纳投名状 结兄弟义
join the brotherhood today.
死生相托 吉凶相救
We take the blood oath.
福祸相依 患难相扶
We pledge our lives.
外人乱我兄弟者
Those who bring us harm...
视投名状 必杀之
must die.
兄弟乱我兄弟者
A brother who harms another brother...
视投名状 必杀之
must die.
天地作证 山河为盟
Heaven and earth bear witness...
有违此誓 天地诛之
and strike dead any man who breaks his oath.
人和一心
We share one heart...
他后来跟我说
He told me later that...
其实他不相信投名状
he didn't believe in the pledge.
我问 那你信什么
I asked him what he believed in.
他说他相信二哥
He said Er-Hu...
还有我
and me.
等一会儿 把这鞋带上
Wait! Take these shoes with you.
路上要小心啊
Take care!
以后娘再也看不见你了
Mother may never see you again.
妈 我走了
Good-bye, ma.
二虎哥
Er Hu!
石锦标带着一群人走了
Shi and his men are leaving!
就留下一句话
He said that he'd rather die...
说誓死也不投清兵
than serve the Qing army!
听说你带一营兵
Your entire battalion perished...
在鹤川伏击太平军
in the battle against the Taiping rebels in Hechuan...
竟然全军覆没
and you disappeared for 2 months!
两个月没见 还敢回来
How dare you return now?
陈大人
My Lord Chan.
鹤川一战
Lord Jiang sent the Kui army...
姜大人派魁字营在我左翼护守
to aid us in the battle at the Hechuan.
何魁临阵畏敌退兵三十里
But they left us to fend for ourselves.
我一营的兄弟就这样眼睁睁的死光了
My men were slaughtered on the battlefield.
全军覆没
All your men died...
就你一人活着
but you alone survived?
我不死
I stayed alive...
就是要回来见你
just to see you again...
姜大人
Lord Jiang.
你们几个人啊
How many men do you have?
八百
800.
再给我八百
Give me another 800...
十五日之内 我攻下舒城
and I will capture Shu City within 15 days.
军中无戏言
Don't jest with me!
十日
10!
十日攻下舒城
I will capture Shu City in 10 days !
好
Well...
我
then...
我再给你一千五百精兵
I'll give you 1,500 fine soldiers...
但是没有军饷
but no wages.
不要军饷
We don't need wages;
攻下城 一半的东西归我们
we get half the spoils once we capture Shu City.
庞青云
Pang Qing-Yun.
你字“鹿山” 就叫“山字营”吧
Name your army "Shan".
谢三位大人
Thank you, my lords.
你在赌
You're gambling...
拿八百条人命在赌
with 800 lives.
打仗本身就是赌
War is a gamble.
我不赌
I won't gamble.
这一千五百兵 是陈公的家底
My 1500 men are the last of Lord Chen's army.
打没了
If we lose them...
陈公在朝廷说话就没底气
my lord will be powerless at the imperial court.
你如何才肯出手
Make me an offer!
我的兵
My army...
只给你壮声势
will only give you a semblance of multitude.
这是你唯一可以赢的机会
This is your only chance for victory.
不然
Otherwise...
魁字营永远都把你踩在脚下
you'll forever be at the mercy of the Kui army!
大哥
Big brother!
都是坏的
They're all useless.
对面有两百枝洋枪
We'll be facing 200 rifles.
仗很难打
The odds are against us.
要赢 只有一个办法
To win, we need to attack.
豁出去 破他们的枪阵
Break through their firing line...
贴过去 跟他们斗狠
Engage them in hand to hand combat.
兄弟们
Brothers!
告诉他 谁最狠
Tell him who's the toughest?
我最狠
We are!
两军相隔三百大步
The enemy will be 300 paces away.
火枪的射程是两百步
Rifles have a range of 200 paces...
弓箭只有一百步
arrows have only 100.
我们要两百个兄弟冲在前面
We'll need a vanguard of 200 men...
弓箭手紧跟其后 再冲两百
to run straight at the firing range.
听见枪声不要躲 继续冲
They must not dodge the bullets...
拼命的贴上去
but must use their bodies as shields...
为弓箭手
so that our archers...
赢得这一百步
who run behind them can get within range.
很多兄弟会死
Many brothers will die in the process.
我去
I'm in!
有谁跟我去
Who's with me?
愿意去的有安家费 死了两份
Die and your family will receive double your wages!
活下来三份
Live and you receive triple!
能发财还不去呀
Don't you want to be rich?
是爷们就放个响屁
Where are the real men?!
来啊
Come on!
妈的 豁出去了
Damn it, count me in!
我也去
Me too, I'm in...
算我一个 我去
Count me in...
我也去
me too...
我去 我也去
I'm in...
进舒城
Take Shu City!
抢钱 抢粮 抢娘们
Take their money, their food, their women!
进舒城
Take Shu City!
抢钱 抢粮 抢娘们
Take their money, their food, their women!
寡众悬殊
You're vastly outnumbered...
胜负已分 天恩浩荡
victory is already ours.
投降便可免你一死
Surrender and your life will be spared.
杀
Kill them!!!
放
Fire!
杀
Kill them!!!
放
Fire!
杀
Kill them!!!
快死光了 还不去
They're dying out there! Let's go!
你给我记住
Shut up and listen!
战场上只有一个是头
There's only one commander in a battle!
杀
Kill them!!!
放箭
Shoot!
放 放箭
哥
Brother!
预备
Prepare!
蒙马眼
Blinders on!
他是在用命 逼我出手
He's using himself to goad me into combat.
冲
Go!
救大哥
Big brother!
大哥
Brother...
不要拔 不要拔出来
No! Don't pull that out!
抓紧
Hold steady!
我们是真的要死在这里了
We're really going to die this time.
我们纳了投名状
We're blood brothers!
不求同生 但求同死
We die as one!
说得对
That's right!
死也要拉个垫背的
We might as well take a few with us...
杀一个算一个
as we go down!
冲出去
Let's go...
杀
Kill them!
疯子
It's madness!
八百人居然把五千人给搅乱了
800 men manage to upset an army of 5000...
有得打
We can win!
我们太需要一场胜利了
We really need a victory badly!
跟着我 冲
Follow me!
午阳
Wu-Yang!
狄大人
Lord Di...
庞青云也算是个福将啊
Pang Qing-Yun must be blessed.
庞青云
Pang...
咱俩也算是有缘份
Fate has brought us together again.
算你押宝押中了
How fortunate of you to capture Shu City...
舒城一战闯出了个名堂
you have made a name for yourself.
庞青云
Pang...
再给你五个营的兵力 怎么样
how does 5 more battalions sound?
我再锦上添花
On top of that...
陆大山 在
Lu Da-Shan... Sir
今后归你调谴
will be under your command.
谢大人
Thank you, My Lord.
庞青云
Pang Qing-Yun.
有个魁字营的老朋友在等你
Your old friend from the Kui army is waiting for you.
何魁
He Kui.
在
Sir.
参见大人
Greetings, my lords.
庞将军 久违了
It's been a long time, General Pang.
既然是老交情
It'll be a reunion of old allies...
那就继续联手
with you leading the attack...
你攻城他接防
and him bringing up the rear.
他来了 我们怎么分
How do we divide the spoils?
狄大人
Lord Di and...
陈大人
Lord Chen...
不会有意见吧
no objections I trust?
我怕他跑得太慢追不上
I'm afraid he won't be able to keep up!
先取苏州再打南京 怎样
We'll take Suzhou, and then Nanking!
他们笑什么
What are they laughing at?
南京是敌人的心脏
Nanking is the enemy's capital.
欲破南京 先取苏州
To topple Nanking, we must first take Suzhou.
仗打完了 他们赚什么
Since they have nothing to gain when the war is over...
他们是不会让我们打苏州的
they won't let us take Suzhou.
那我们打他们管得了吗
If we attack, they can't stop us.
安插魁字营
The Kui army was precisely sent...
就是为了监视我们
to keep an eye on us.
快来呀 他们回来了
They've returned!
小五
Xiao-Wu
Xiao-Wu, Xiao-Wu...
小五的鞋
Xiao-Wu's shoes...
小五
Xiao-Wu...
小七
Xiao-Qi?!
小七 我的儿啊
Xiao-Qi... my boys...
我们不再是土匪
We were no longer bandits.
他说 土匪只为自己兄弟去杀人
He said a bandit kills for his own interests.
而英雄却可以为别人牺牲
But a hero sacrifices for others.
我想当英雄
I wanted to be a hero.
你瘦了
You've lost weight.
大哥说 这一走三年就回来
Big brother says, we'll only be away for 3 years.
我知道你不喜欢这里
I know you've never liked it here.
等打完了仗
When the war is over...
我带你去一个好地方过日子
I'll find us a better place to settle down.
那大哥呢
Where's Brother Pang?
在村外睡 他说不进来了
He's staying outside the village tonight.
我们明天一早就出发
We'll leave tomorrow morning.
记住
Remember...
兵不厌诈
Winning is all that matters!
开始
Begin!
杀
Kill them!
进城接防
We're here to take over.
让兄弟们逍遥三天
Give the men 3 days leave to pillage!
抢钱 抢粮 抢娘们
Let them take money, food and women!
出来呀 仗已经打完了
You can come out now, the war is over.
出来呀
Come.
出来吧 别害怕
Come, don't be afraid.
没吃东西吧
Have you eaten?
饿不饿
You hungry?
放开我 你们干嘛
Let go!
你们干嘛 小姐
What are you doing?!
你们看什么看 快搭把手啊
Don't just stay there! Give me a hand!
不要啊
No!...
不要啊 别过来
Don't touch me!...
狗子 我走了啊
Gouzi, I'm leaving!
放开我
Let me go...
庞大哥
Brother Pang.
走 干嘛
Move! What is it?
你们凭什么抓我
Why am I being arrested?
走 怎么啦
Go! What is it?!
召集百姓 就地正法
Gather the people for a public execution!
二虎哥
Brother Zhao!
大哥 怎么了
Brother, what's this about?
奸淫民女
They raped 2 women.
进城抢三天 这是规矩
They were given three days of pillage, this was bound to happen!
从今天起这种事不能在我们的军队里发生
From this day on, I will not tolerate such conduct under my command!
我们一直都是这样的呀
It's what we've always done.
以前是匪 今天是兵
We're soldiers now, not bandits.
匪气不改 什么也做不成
We must better ourselves or we won't achieve anything!
如果我们这样做
If we allow this to happen...
跟魁字营那班畜生有什么区别
we're no better than those Kui bastards!
规矩总有开始的一天 就是今天
Today is the day we start setting down some rules!
我们刚刚杀了那些女人的家里人
We've just killed their families!
毁了她们的家
Now you want to protect them?
你现下反过来保护他们
By killing our own?
那以后有谁来帮你卖命
No one will risk their lives fighting for you after this!
大哥
Brother...
听我的吧 你看他们
Listen to me, look at them!
他们懂了
They've learned their lesson.
用不着杀头的嘛 对不对
There's no need to kill them, right?
在干什么
Don't just kneel there!
赶快说你们认错
Say you're sorry!
大哥 我们错了 我们不敢了
Big brother, we were wrong, we're so sorry...
狗子 我听不到 再说
Gouzi! Say it again!
狗子 快呀 承认错呀 说呀
Gouzi, say you're sorry! Say it!
快说啊 狗子
Come on, Gouzi...
大哥 我们错了
Big brother, we're sorry!
大哥 他们知道错了
Big brother, they know they're wrong.
算了吧
Have mercy.
从前我做官的时候
When I was still a civil servant...
在街上看见一个捕快
I saw a soldier...
抓住一个穷人 见着就打
beating a peasant on the street...
打得遍体鳞伤 浑身是血
...until the man was covered with his own blood.
没有任何理由
There was no reason for it...
就是因为他穷
except that the man was poor.
而这个穷人 并没有怨言
But the poor man never retaliated.
好像一切都是天公地道的
He accepted it as part of his lot in life.
从那天我就发誓
I promised myself that day...
如果我作主
I would never allow...
这种事就决不能再发生
something like that to happen again!
你们投军
You joined the army...
是为了不让别人欺负
because you don't want to be bullied.
现在我告诉你
Let me tell you.
不光你们
not only you but everyone...
全天下的百姓都不能让人欺负
men and women alike should be free from oppression!
我们要做的是这样的大事
That's what we're fighting for!
直到那一天
That day...
他才终于说出了他心里的未来
he finally revealed his dream for the future.
他告诉我
He said...
以前不做是时候不到
he waited because he was afraid
怕我们不懂
we wouldn't understand.
我懂
But I did.
住手
Stop!
我的人轮到你杀吗
Don't you touch my men!
滚开
Back off!
大哥
Brother...
算了吧
Please...
你们的命是谁的
Who do you owe your lives to?
是谁的
Who?!
大哥的
Big brother!
你跟我娘该怎么说
What will you tell my mother?
眼睛闭起来
Closes your eyes.
我会很快
I'll be quick.
午阳哥 你跟我娘该怎么说
Brother Jiang... What will you tell my mother?
别告诉我娘
Don't tell my mother!
要是我能为这个未来而死
How I wish I could sacrifice my life
那该有多好
for this future of his.
我一直以为
I used to think...
打仗抢东西才会杀人
we only kill to survive.
现在才明白
Now I see that...
心变好了也要杀人
we must also kill in order to do good.
我答应你尽快结束这场战争
We must end this war in 3 months.
我们三个月打下苏州
We must take Suzhou!
唷 孤子
Look! The abandoned!
你怎么跟庞青云一样
You're behaving like Pang,
顾头不顾腚啊
too ambitious.
几千人就想打苏州 不自量力
Thinks he can take Suzhou with a few thousand men?
我是替陈公着想
I'm worried for you, Lord Chen
断了根 又无粮草
With no supplies or reinforcements...
死定了
He's dead for sure!
胜负往往在瞬息万变之中
There's a fine line between winning and losing.
如果在这儿 连下去
If I add the right piece... here.
庞青云在朝廷一步登天
Pang might just climb to the top...
到时候
with his next victory.
我会让庞青云连回去吗
Do you think I'd let Pang return to the fold?
弃子
Leaving him stranded...
对大家都有好处
benefits everyone.
苏州城 一年后
"Suzhou City, One Year Later"
你们都在干什么
What's keeping all of you?!
你们再不来 我就卸了你们的腿
Come get me now or I'll break your legs!
苏州城已成死局
Suzhou is at an impasse;
攻守都得死
both sides will starve to death.
魁字营就在城外等着呢
The Kui army are waiting to swoop like vultures!
你还要赌到什么时候
How much longer can you afford to gamble?
猪倌
Butcher...
你给我唱首歌吧
...sing me a song.
听说
I heard that...
听说有个叫耶稣的先生
there is a man named Jesus.
每天中午
Each day at noon...
都给苏州城姓黄的
He gives the Taiping general Huang in Suzhou...
五张大饼 两口肥猪
5 loaves of bread and 2 fat pigs.
随便就随便那么一分
He would then divide the food casually...
就能让五千多个人
and somehow he feeds all 5000 people...
全都吃饱了
Everyone is fed.
饼怎么分就是分不完
Their bread never runs out.
猪 猪每天都在下崽儿
And new piglets are being born everyday.
坐下
Sit down!
不如我进城杀了黄文金
I'll steal into the city and kill Huang.
去的人没一个活着回来
Those who tried never came back.
我不许你们去牺牲
I won't put more lives at risk.
我去找狄公
I'll go ask Lord Di...
要粮要炮
for food and weapons.
我们攻打苏州 已经是违抗军令
But we've defied their orders by attacking Suzhou.
我对他们还有用
I'm still of some use to them.
两位回去吧
Please leave now.
给我粮 我就能拿下苏州
Give me provisions and I'll seize Suzhou!
我的兵只能战死 不能饿死
My men may die in battles but not from hunger!
我求你啦
Please, I beg you!
大人说啦 他根本不知道苏州在打仗
My lord says he didn't know Suzhou was at war.
去魁字营
To the Kui army!
大哥 不能求他们
We can't go begging to them!
想不通你就回去
Then I will go alone!
快 快走
Let's go!
快
Quick!
Hurry...
来 抓住
Take my hand!
他们想爬进城
They tried to steal into the city;
都说城里有吃的
they all said there was food inside.
不行 我得进去
I must go in for myself.
给我粮食 枪炮
Give me provisions and weapons...
我们作笔交易
I'll make you a deal.
我不给你
I don't need that -
苏州城也是我的
Suzhou is already mine.
我说的是
I'm talking about...
南京
Nanking.
仗我打 城我攻 人我死
My men do the fighting and the dying!
魁字营只要站在后边作作样子
All you have to do is stand behind us.
南京 一人一半
We divide Nanking between us;
我们携手进城
we enter the city together...
你甘心一辈子
unless you want to be under.
被那三个老头儿踩在脚下
the power of those three old men forever.
我们一定要先打下南京
We must capture Nanking...
让朝廷知道打南京跟何魁无关
before the Kui army arrives to take credit.
可是我们只有十天粮
But we only have 10 days' supplies.
所以要快
We act quickly
两天 拿下苏州
We capture Suzhou within 2 days!
老天真好
The heavens are good to me...
这时候把你送过来
sending you to me tonight.
保平安的
It can protect you.
卯时 看不到城里的红烟
If you don't see a red flare by dawn from inside the city...
我的人会带你走
my men will take you to safety.
跟大哥 午阳他们说
Tell big brother and Wu-Yang that...
二虎想当英雄
Er-Hu wanted to be a hero.
将军回来了
General Pang is back!...
庞将军 粮食已经送来了
Sir, the provisions have arrived!
二虎将军进城了
General Zhao has entered the city.
说卯时看见红烟
He said if we see a red flare by dawn...
就代表他成功了
it means he has succeeded.
兄弟 跟你要的货带了吗
My friend, did you bring the goods?
都说城里有粮食
They say we have food in the city.
再这么耗下去 就得人吃人
But we may start eating each other soon.
我答应过兄弟们 吃饱穿暖
I promised they would be clothed and fed...
三年打完仗回家享福
and could go home within 3 years.
现在五年了
It's been 5 years now...
明天卯时 攻城
We attack at dawn.
嫂子
Lian.
我喜欢看人的脸
I like to study different faces...
苏州被围
but I haven't seen a new face...
我已经一年没见过生人了
since Suzhou came under siege a year ago.
听说这次送鸦片的是个陌生人
I hear the opium dealer is a new face
这个东西 我已经戒了
but I don't use opium anymore -
它只能止痛
it only eases the pain.
我妻子的坟墓就在城外的小树林里
My wife's grave is just outside the city in the woods.
我想去看
I long to see her...
却不能看
but can't.
你能明白一个囚徒的心思吗
Do you know what it's like to be a prisoner?
苏州城就像一个大牢 已经很久了
Suzhou has become one big prison...
我想出 但出不去
I can't get out...
你想进 也进不来
you can't get in either...
除非
unless...
我让你进来
I let you in.
你的同乡
Remember Shi?
你投了清 他跟了我
You joined the Qing army, he followed me.
快
Hurry!
大人 卯时已过
Sir... it's past dawn
备马
Prepare the horses.
送赵夫人
Escort Lady Zhao away.
二虎留下话
Er-hu said that...
说他要当英雄
he wanted to be a hero.
如果我能活下来
If I survive, I will...
娶你
marry you.
外面有四千饿疯了的士兵
4,000 soldiers are outside crazed with starvation.
你杀了我
If you kill me...
苏州会变成鬼城 所有的人都要死
you will all die in a blood bath.
我也四千士兵
I too have 4,000 men.
他们将会为守住苏州城每一寸土地
They'll defend every inch of the city...
流尽最后一滴血
to their last drop of blood.
都退下
Stand down.
卸下武器
Lay down your arms.
投降吧
Please surrender!
十一年前
11 years ago...
我卖了祖业 关了生意
I closed my business and sold everything...
投了太平
to join the Taiping rebellion.
从那天起
From that day on...
投降这两个字
the word "surrender"...
就永远的消失了
no longer existed for me!
我不死
As long as I live...
苏州城这个大牢里的人
the people of Suzhou City...
就出不去
will never be free.
让士兵回家务农
Spare my soldiers... let them go home.
不要羞辱城里的百姓
Don't make the civilians suffer.
安心
May you...
上路
go in peace!
预备
Get ready!
二虎 二虎
Er-Hu... Er-Hu...!
赵二虎
Zhao Er-Hu!
我要见赵二虎
I want to see Zhao Er-Hu!
馒头
We want bread! Bread!...
咱们真的要收编他们啊
Are we going to conscript them?
他们不会同意的
They will never agree.
四千个俘虏 四千张嘴
There are 4,000 captives.
你想动用多少军粮喂饱他们
How much of our food will you give them?
大哥
Brother...
给他们活路
They surrendered only because...
是他们开城投降的条件
I promised to let them live.
苏州的粮仓早就空了
The city's granaries are empty, and...
我们的粮食只有十天
we have only a 10-day-supply of food.
要留着打南京
We must save it for Nanking.
什么打南京啊
Nanking?
大哥 什么打南京啊
Are we attacking Nanking?
魁字营集结完毕
The Kui army decamped yesterday;
随时都会攻打南京
they will attack Nanking at any moment.
我不识字
I can't read!
不要给我看 告诉我 哪来的粮食
Just tell me where the supplies are from?
哪来的
Where?!
魁字营
The Kui army.
你为什么要跟他们交易啊
How could you make a deal with He Kui?!
这四千人拒绝收编
These solders will never join our army.
打南京
If we attack Nanking...
这苏州城就是空城
Suzhou will be defenseless.
你放心把苏州城交给他们吗
Can you leave the city in their hands?
大哥 你听我说好不好 你听我说
- Listen to me! - No, you listen!
这四千人拿起枪就是兵
These soldiers are our enemies.
馒头 馒头
We want bread! Bread!...
开城门
Open the stores!
给我发粮
Give me what I need.
不行
No!
庞青云
Pang Qing-Yun!
我早知道你是什么人
I knew you were a liar!
你看这馒头
This bread...
本来是我们兄弟要吃的
was meant for our brothers.
你要分一半给这四千人
But you want to give half to the captives...
再分一半给城里的百姓
and then the other half to the civilians.
兄弟们围城围了九个月
Our brothers have fought for 9 months...
饿了九个月
and starved for 9 months!
你说这馒头
You tell me...
是给我们还是他们
Who should get this bread, them or us?
我不管
I don't care!
发粮
Give them food!
发 发
Now!!!
就一顿
Let them eat.
让他们吃饱
It's their last meal
我答应过要让他们活着
But I promised to spare their lives!
兵不厌诈 这是战争
Winning is all that matters in war!
人无信就是畜生
A man who breaks his word is a beast!
二哥
Brother...
大哥是对的
He's right.
让开
Move!
大哥是对的
He's right
给我让开
Get out of the way!
大哥是对的
He's right.
放开我 放开
Let me go!...
放开我 我答应过要让他们活着
Let me go! I promised to spare their lives!
备箭
Archers!
安静
Quiet!
不能杀
Don't kill them!
再放
Again!
不能杀 不能杀
Don't kill them! Don't kill them!
再放
Again!
那天以后
From that day on...
二哥再也没和我说过一句话
Er-Hu never said another word to me.
我难过 可是
It hurts, but...
大哥是对的
big brother was right.
回家啦
Let's go home!
谁跟我
Who's with me?
二虎 你不能走
Er-Hu, you can't go.
我们还要去打南京呢
We still have to take Nanking.
你要我继续看你杀那些手无寸铁的人
What for? To kill more defenseless people?
他们是兵
They were soldiers.
投降了
They surrendered!
还是兵
They were still soldiers!
你还记得过去你跟我们讲什么
Do you remember what you said to us?
你说你要找个地方
You said everyone deserves...
让老百姓不会因为穷就挨打
to be free even the poor!
你现在做了什么
What have you done now?
你现在就在这里
You have ordered right here...
杀了四千个穷人 你知道吗
the massacre of 4,000 poor people?! You know that?!
不是穷人 谁会去打仗
Only the poor are willing to go to war!
小顺子 小五子 小七子 哪个不是穷人
Which one of us weren't poor!
但他们是兵
Those men were soldiers.
是兵就会死
Soldiers are prepared to die.
可南京城 上百万的是老百姓
But the millions in Nanking are just civilians.
何魁先进去就完了
If He Kui reaches them first, they're dead!
打南京 我需要你
I need your help to take Nanking.
你不要走
Please don't go.
你一走可是兵变啊
If you go, it will be mutiny.
这山字营的兄弟就会自相残杀
The Shan brothers will turn on each other!
你知道那后果
Think about the consequences!
不要逼我
Don't force my hand!
谁敢动二哥 我跟他拼了
I'll kill anyone who touches Er-Hu!
二哥 千万不可以走
Brother, you must not leave.
你走了 我们这个家就真的没了
If you leave now... ours pledge will be broken
二虎
Er-Hu!
何魁的兵已经出发了
The Kui army has already left.
如果我们再不走就来不及了
We must leave now or we'll be too late!
我向你保证
I promise you...
我们打完南京
after Nanking...
我会放下刀
there'll be peace.
将来你会知道
One day you'll see that...
我今天的决定是对的
my decisions today were right.
好
Fine.
进南京 我看着你
I'll be watching you in Nanking.
你对 我跪还你
If you're right, I'll kneel before you.
你错 我就杀了你
But if you're wrong, I'll kill you.
走
Let's go!
俺
We...
赵二虎 庞青云
Zhao Er-Hu... Pang Qing-Yun...
姜午阳 弟兄三人
Jiang Wu-Yang... three brothers as one...
杀
Attack!
礼花满天 南京攻陷
Victory is ours, Nanking is ours!
礼炮一响 太后吉祥
Long live the Empress Dowager!
南京 降城后一个月
One month after the capture of Nanking.
安心上路
Go in peace.
我们发过誓
We swore an oath...
一辈子都是山字营的人
to remain loyal to the Shan regiment.
只要这世界上 有人挨饿被欺负
As long as there is hunger, oppression...
有人是非不分
and injustice...
我们山字营永远都在
the Shan regiment will fight!
发军饷
Dole out the wages!
张文方 五两
Zhang Wen-Fang, 5 taels.
王小三
Wang Xiao-San...
二虎 你知不知道你在做什么
Er-Hu, what are you doing?!
私分朝廷军饷是重罪
The money belongs to the imperial coffers!
我们进了南京之后 有一半是军饷
We agreed to take Nanking and give half of the spoils to our men.
你不发 我帮你发
If you won't do it! I will!
你们要记住
Remember!
军队里面就只有一个头
The Shan regiment has only one leader!
这个头 就是庞大人庞将军
And that's General Pang!
还不赶快谢谢他
Show him your gratitude!
谢谢庞大人
Thank you General!
再说
Again!
谢谢庞大人
Thank you General!!!
继续发钱
Back to the wages...
王小三 三两四钱
Wang Xiao-San, 3 taels 4 mace.
王郎 四两
Wang Long, 4 taels
何大人
My lord.
打南京 你给他粮
He needed your help to take Nanking.
进了南京 你成要饭的了
Now you're at his mercy.
我迟早要杀了他
I will kill him eventually!
一步慢 步步慢
You're always a step behind
太后要他做两江总督
The Empress is making him Governor of Jiangsu.
那又怎么样
So what?
何魁 这回我帮不了你啦
He Kiu, even I can't help you this time.
只要我们把赵二虎给拉过来
We just need to get Zhao Er-Hu on our side...
两江总督 他肯定做不长
and Pang's downfall is ensured!
赵二虎 庞青云 姜午阳
Zhao Er-Hu... Pang Qing-Yun... Jiang Wu-Yang...
弟兄三人
three brothers as one...
喝酒 喝
Drink up!
歃血为盟神灵鉴
Heaven and earth be our witnesses.
义字当先对地天
We take a blood oath, pledge our lives.
不求同生求同死
We were born apart but die as one.
祸福共当
Loyalty through good times...
肝胆悬
and bad.
赵大人 仗是你打的
General Zhao, you did the fighting.
功劳让别人独吞
but he took the credit.
你恨吗
How can you live with that?
怎样
So what?
这戏里唱的是兄弟情
This opera is about brotherhood.
既是兄弟 他为什么把你锁进祠堂
He's your brother, yet he had you in chains?
让你背信弃义 任天下人耻笑
He forced you to break your word and made a fool out of you.
割了这把草
Make him pay.
你我联手 一了百了 共用南京
If we join forces and Nanking can be ours.
好好想想吧 赵大人
Give it some thought.
何将军是在为你盘算
General He is only thinking of your future.
来
Come over here!
打的好
Revenge is sweet!
他抽你两鞭子的仇好报
Shallow wounds heal...
可你心里的恨难解
but deep wounds fester.
赵大人 慢慢想 不急
General Zhao, take your time to think it over.
何大人
General He.
你是不是在想
You must be wondering...
从宫门外走到这儿需要多久
how long it takes to get from the gates to here?
年轻时候 我头一次站在宫门外
I had the same thought the first time...
也是这么想啊
I stood outside the palace gates.
可等真的走到这儿
By the time I reached this far...
已经是两鬓斑白
my hair had already turned gray
用了整整三十年了
it took me 30 years.
可惜啊 走不动啦
Now I'm too old to walk.
小李子
Li Lianying.
太后说 你还年轻
The Empress said your youth is an asset;
君臣相伴会长久
you will serve us for a long time.
太后还说 收复南京
The Empress also said.
庞青云劳苦功高
Pang should be commended for the capture of Nanking.
赏黄马褂一件
He will receive the Golden Robes.
加封两江总督 钦此
and appointed Governor of Jiangsu!
还不快谢
Show your gratitude!
臣 庞青云
Your servant Pang requests that...
启奏太后免除两江辖区三年赋税
the people of Jiangsu be exempt from 3 years of taxes
修生养民
to recover from the war.
准奏
Request granted!
谢太后
Thank you your Highness.
苏州杀人 南京活人
You're responsible for the Suzhou massacre...
庞大人是君子豹变
yet you saved the people of Nanking.
果然是辅国良臣啊
Lord Pang, you're surely adaptable.
那是因为庞大人和朝廷不属任何派系
The Empress favors Lord Pang because
才得太后的垂青
he does not belong to any fractions.
南京是给了你
Nanking may be yours,
可姜大人气得是卧病南方
But you've offended Lord Jiang and He Kui along the way.
何魁又蠢蠢欲动
Now, without allies...
你 镇得住吗
how long do you think you'll last?
庞大人 我翻了翻黄历
Lord Pang, I checked the lunar calendar.
四月初八午时上任
The 8th day of the 4th month...
利国利民 利己
will be the most auspicious time for your inauguration
大吉
...and for all.
要想有所作为
Before you can do good...
庞大人 你得好好活着
Lord Pang, you must look after yourself!
好好活着
You must look after yourself.
我有公务在身 告辞了
I must leave now, My lords.
叛乱虽平
The unrest has subsided,
可地方督府个个手握重兵
but the local militias wield too much power.
庞大人 这太后不放心
Lord Pang, the Empress is concerned.
山字营带头裁军
The Shan regiment will be the first to disband.
好
Good!
庞大人跟军队做了了断
Once you sever your old ties...
便可专心履行你的总督的事务啦
you can devote yourself to your duties as governor.
你兄弟赵二虎 在苏州说要走
Your brother Zhao Er-Hu threatened to desert the army in Suzhou.
结果呢
He almost created...
一呼百应
a mutiny there.
在南京 又私分朝廷军饷
In Nanking, he doled out funds meant for the royal coffers.
你山字营姓赵啊
Does he own your regiment?!
大人 危险
Be careful, my lord!
我这一生 如履薄冰
I've walked on thin ice my whole life.
你说我能走到对岸吗
Do you think I can safely cross over?
你醒了
You're awake.
我醒了
Yes, I am.
可能真的是他们对的
Perhaps they're right.
南京
Nanking...
根本不需要我这种人
doesn't need someone like me.
我想回家
I want to go home.
你愿意吗
Will you come with me?
我不需要了
I don't need this anymore.
什么事
What is it?
二爷 出大事了
Bad news, my lord!
魁字营要反 何魁要杀庞大人
He Kui plans to assassinate Lord Pang!
没事
It's nothing.
二爷
General Zhao.
大哥
Big brother!
二爷
General Zhao.
大哥
Big brother!
二爷
General Zhao.
大哥呢
Where's he?
庞大人去了京城 还没回来
Lord Pang has not returned from the imperial court.
您决定了
Decided?
那我去了
Then I'm off.
三爷
General Jiang.
他们是谁
Who are they?
京城调来的御林军
Guards sent by the imperial court.
红色那块桌布 一会儿赶快给我铺上
Cover that table with the red cloth.
偏厅偏厅 一会儿还有这个
Move these vases as well.
赶紧的
Hurry!
三爷 怎么 有客人
Brother Wu Yang You have guests coming?
您不知道 庞大人请赵大人吃饭
General Pang has invited General Zhao to dine.
他们和好了
They've reconciled!
大哥回来了
Is big brother home?
说是下午就回来
He should return by the afternoon...
为什么这府上的侍卫全换人了
why have they replaced all the guards?
赵将军 慢走
General Zhao, wait!
赵将军
Sir...
刚才收到密报 庞大人要做两江总督
We received news that...
何魁要兵变
He Kui plans to assassinate Lord Pang.
庞大人进不了城
He must not return to the city now
约你到城外江浦镇商量对策
he asked you to meet him at Jianpu.
让午阳带人 到江浦镇集合
Tell Wu-Yang to bring the others and meet us there.
午阳
Wu-Yang.
我找二哥
Where's Er-Hu?
二哥
He...
去找庞大哥了
went to see Brother Pang.
你有事瞒我
You're up to something!
院子里多了很多生人
What's with all those new guards?
你要动二哥
You're going to kill Er-Hu...
就为了嫂子
all because of Lian?!
你忘了投名状
Have you forgotten our pledge?!
二哥什么时候到
When will Er-Hu arrive?
给我最后时限
Tell me when!
亥时
Nightfall...
亥时二虎到
He'll be here by nightfall.
你等我
Wait for me!
你吓了我一跳
You scared me.
嫂子 午阳来与你告别
Lian, I'm here to say goodbye.
你要走吗
Are you leaving?
我送你
No, you are.
我去哪儿
But where to?
我在等二虎回来呢
I'm waiting for Er-Hu...
我刚给他做了晚饭
I've just prepared dinner.
大哥为了你 要杀二哥
Big brother is going to kill Er-Hu over you.
不可能 不会的
No, it can't be!
你下来
Come down here.
我不
No.
我要把这个纱帘弄好
I have to finish draping this frame.
你见过这么好看的纱帘吗
Have you ever seen such beautiful fabric?
我都十几年没见过这么好看的纱帘了
I haven't seen one in years.
我昨天在铺里 还看见一个红色的
I saw the red one in a shop yesterday...
我想要绿的 也想要红的
but I also wanted the green one.
我问二虎怎么办呢
I asked Er-Hu what to do
二虎说
He said...
今年绿的 明年红的
green for this year and red for the next.
我明年就二十九岁了
I'll be 29 next year.
打了十四年仗
I lived through 14 years of war...
我没饿死 也没被砍死
didn't starve to death or get killed.
那是我命大
I've been lucky!
明年还要挂红色的纱帘
I still have to hang the red curtain next year.
我明年还要挂红色的纱帘
下来
Come down!
你不会杀我的 我不准你杀我
You wouldn't kill me... I won't let you!
我好不容易活到现在
It wasn't easy for me to survive!
你为什么要杀死我
Why must you kill me?
我不杀你 怎么救二哥
If I don't kill you... how will I save Er-Hu?
你杀了我 就能救二哥吗
Can you really save him by killing me?
我不知道
I don't know...
但我只能这么做
but it's all I can do.
你从小就跟着我
I watched you grow up.
你不会的 你不会的
You wouldn't do it... You won't!
午阳 你不会忍心杀我的
I know you can't kill me...
你不会的
You wouldn't do it...
外人乱我兄弟者
Anyone who harms our brothers...
你不会杀我的
You can't kill me!
视投名状
must be...
必杀之
killed!
五年前
5 years ago...
一百零八个人 从一个小村子出来
108 men left their village to join the army...
打仗拼命就为了一口饭吃
risking their lives for a little food.
这就是山字营最早的兄弟
They were the first to join the Shan army
领头的就是我们三个
The three of us were their leaders.
今天 我选了一个好地方送你走
Today, I found a good place to free you
我跟你说过
I told you...
总有一天 你会明白我是对的
there will come a day when you'll see that I was right.
每年这个时候 我都请你喝酒
Each year at this time, I'll drink with you.
告诉你 我这一年都做了什么
I'll tell you what I've done in the past year.
我刚才从京城回来
I just returned from the palace.
为咱们的百姓
The people of Jiangsu have been...
免了三年的征税
spared from taxes for 3 years.
明年 明年我保证
Next year, I promise...
每一个百姓都吃得饱
no one will go hungry.
你迟早会明白
You'll understand eventually
小七 狗子
that Xiao-Qi and Gouzi...
死的是值得的
didn't die in vain...
苏州的四千人
and the massacre of the 4000 captives...
死的也是值得的
was necessary.
你
And you...
You...
也是值得的
You will not die in vain.
苏州你要造反
You defied my orders in Suzhou.
我本可以杀你
I could have killed you then,
可是我不舍得
but I couldn't do it.
可是现下朝廷
But now it's the imperial court...
朝廷要你
that wants you dead.
何魁
He Kui!
你说 我怎么办
What choice do I have?
你出来
Come out here!
好兄弟 二虎
My brother...
安心上路
go in peace.
大哥
Brother...
大哥 你不用动二哥
Big brother, you don't need to kill Er-Hu!
大哥
Brother!
你不用动二哥
you don't need to kill Er-Hu!
嫂子已经死了
Lian is dead!
你不用动二哥了
You don't have to kill Er-Hu!
嫂子已经死了
Lian is already dead...
你没有杀二哥的理由了
no reason to kill Er-Hu now!
大哥
Brother!
嫂子已经死了
Lian is dead!
圣主承天
The gods bless this day.
作君师于下土
Joining the ranks of those that went before...
良臣当国
a great servant to the empire.
行政教于家邦
To lead by example and serve his people.
庞青云荣任两江总督之庆典
The inauguration of Pang Qing-Yun as Governor of Jiangsu will take place...
庚午四月初八午时
at noon on this day, the 8th of the 4th month.
一个篱笆得三个桩
A fence needs three pillars.
姜大人不在 真是不热闹啊
It's not the same without Lord Jiang here.
已时三刻
A quarter to 12.
停
Stand down!
兄弟杀我兄弟者
A brother who harms another brother...
必杀之
must die!
兄弟杀我兄弟者 必杀之
A brother who harms another brother must die.
时辰到了
It's time.
你别再逼我
Don't push me!
兄弟杀我兄弟者
A brother who harms another brother...
必杀之
must die!
午阳
Wu-Yang!
我求你 别再打了
I beg you stop!
兄弟杀我兄弟者 必杀之
A brother who harms another brother must die.
庞青云
Pang Qing-Yun!
庞青云是个人材
Pang has talent
可不懂为官之道
but doesn't know how things work.
南京是重镇
Nanking is of vital importance
太后想安定天下
to the peace of the country.
怎会倚仗一个外人
The Empress would never entrust it to an outsider.
可惜啊 这都是命
Pity... such is life.
午时已到 鸣炮
Noon is here! Salute cannons, fire!
投名状
Honor our pledge...
快
now!
刺庞者 姜午阳是也
I, Jiang Wu-Yang, killed Pang Qing-Yun!
在那一刻
At that moment...
我脑子里只有结拜时的一句话
My mind went back to the day we took the blood oath.
生不同生 死必同死
We are born apart but we shall die as one.
一百八人 人无同面 面面峥嵘
Our origins are different...
一百八人 人合一心 心心皎洁
but our hearts act as one.
乐必同乐 生不同生 死必同死
In good times and bad...in life and in death.
既列名于天上 无贻笑于人间
We honor our pledge.
报应分明 神天共察
With Heaven and earth as our witness.
但愿生生相会 世世相逢
We shall live and die as blood brothers...
两江总督庞青云
Governor of Jiangsu, Pang Qing-Yun...
于1870年7月26日遇刺身亡
was assassinated on the 26th of July, 1870.
刺客姜午阳两个月后被凌迟处死
His assassin Jiang Wu-Yang was executed 2 months later.